AI GENERATED!. Hi Daniel's taking us.
So
just take something and then.
You take these sweets all right.
Upcoming
Guy,
what's a Children just like sweets.
I can see all the little.
the
Great.
OK
OK.
Yes,
you can put her back by 1 o'clock,
is it easily
so that
she can arrive there by 3 o'clock.
She'll have something of her own
for
lunch.
Oh
And even if you go late,
it doesn't matter.
As long as she comes back at 3 o'clock or 4 o'clock,
will she be able to get back to your house?
Yes she will.
A bad too.
Thank you.
But
Is there a direct uh?
Like.
For you to go direct.
There are trains that are going by train.
Or by car.
I'm driving down by car.
So is there a direct route,
or you have to go wire?
I'll be going from Milton Keynes.
I think there is a direct road.
That's a direct route.
How much time do you take?
About 2 hours I think.
From here
from here to Cambridge.
I'm asking from here if you go to Cambridge,
she can meet you at the station.
We can arrange that in Cambridge in case if you find
that they're going to London and this is going to take too much time.
Because if you go to London now,
say,
to London
and then to Cambridge,
it will take 4 hours for you to drive.
But supposing you go direct from here to Cambridge.
Then how much time will it take?
That's,
that's easy,
because I'm
driving away from here tonight because I have to work
at a children's camp tonight and early tomorrow morning.
So then it takes me maybe an hour and a half from the place I'm at to go to Cambridge.
From here to Cambridge is only 1 hour and a half.
No,
from,
from Milton Keynes where I'm at a camp,
a children's camp,
then it's an hour and a half from there to Cambridge tomorrow morning.
Oh,
I see.
So it would be better if you go direct to Cambridge
and she meets you somewhere.
All right,
so we give
her your telephone number
and you can find her.
All right,
you take her at Cambridge station
and take her around about
and then send her away.
That's all.
Is that all right?
That's better.
So we'll organise that.
So that's better she should go directly by train,
take a return ticket,
and come back.
The same price return ticket to a single ticket,
yes.
piece
This is the sari Kapo I gave you.
I really.
There's little Machinra's Main Main,
let's have one by one.
How are you?
Mother,
will you excuse some people to go for?
I just told them to go for lunch.
None of them will go.
I'm just talking to Masinda Nathan Company.
Alright.
I'll see you slow.
I slow.
There's got one more sweet.
Alright,
Main you can have.
I'm.
Main.
Huh
Oh my
chin now.
Yeah
Oh
Oh.
Ah,
but
My king that.
Yeah
That is my children.
I bought,
so it's too much now,
too much.
And now come.
She's that.
What.
I
I,
you know these things are plastic.
They're,
you see that it is broken.
You can see the white plaster is this?
Oh,
just look at this camouflage.
I do it with the stone also the same way.
They can do,
yes,
but plaster is easy.
You just mould it and then just.
But in India you'll find.
OK.
What's happening to you.
I'm gonna
Oh
I'm like
Matindena,
how are you?
Is he all right?
It was all right.
It was better last week,
mother.
It seems to be better last week and was less good here you can see it kind of got cold,
I believe.
Yeah
Yeah.
be eating in the mouth.
How can you call that?
Oh
Oh,
It's one the most.
You just take the car.
Look at this spot.
Just see please.
All right,
take it.
Oh
All the children are here.
The in the map.
What's that?
Now,
Cathy's all right now.
She's all right.
Thank God she's all right.
It's good.
OK.
She can go back if she wants to.
I'd like to see her.
So now you'll go back to London.
You'll call her home,
you can
see.
Arti,
how are you?
How are you?
Ay,
I think Marina?
It's with you.
How are you?
What's his name?
Samuel,
I gave him a name?
No,
no.
Ah.
A
Hello,
you?
You know me.
Hello,
you know me,
Vian?
Do you know me?
Do you?
Look at that.
What brains they have.
They are going to put you right.
Hello,
Samuel,
come.
That.
Yeah.
One by one,
all right?
Now Mr.
Mainderath is having his feet.
That's all.
Yeah.
Yeah
A.
Hello,
hello,
William.
Why did you crying?
OK.
Hammad.
They catch cold very fast,
these children,
good training for you.
All right?
Yeah.
All right,
all right,
I'm going to take you
now.
It's comfortably fit.
His surname is Rahurikar
because he's from Rahui.
We are going to call him Mr.
Rariar.
All right.
Hmm.
The security
Yeah.
OK
He's remembering,
you see,
many things I think.
Past things.
Oh.
Look at the baby.
That's Samuel.
That's
I take one by one every month.
They want to.
Yeah
Well
I
don't know you.
How are you?
He knows you.
How do they understand vibration?
Yeah
Jenna,
who's going to eat the chana.
That
Does the grapes?
And.
Now one bar,
William,
why were you crying?
Mommy's troubling you or daddy's troubling you?
Who is troubling you,
yeah?
Uh,
see how recognition.
What happened?
What's happening?
Really?
What a nice dress you're wearing,
yeah.
Hello,
Lilia.
How will you?
Hm,
how are you?
I don't see
He's your brother.
Now let's see.
Just put William down here.
Come along,
in the mouth.
See the baby.
No,
no,
no feeling bad I let down.
All right,
It's called like I made it pass me
me to it.
He started understanding.
All right,
come,
watching the,
come.
Oh,
you don't know how to right Uta is a bad boy.
No,
no,
no.
All right.
No,
no,
Rustam doesn't know how to,
he's back.
Hey.
No.
01 more.
a
Oh
I
Yeah
Oh.
All right,
now.
How are you?
Are you all right?
All right,
all right.
That
one by one.
Oh.
All right,
come along,
come along.
Mm.
All of you are,
why are you flying
to get the ice,
right?
Spanish highs
and the.
A ti.
They're very happy.
OK
How about you know,
better.
Mother,
she was very ill about 2 months ago,
quite feverish all over the very hot,
and uh we should be those people that also have been bothering and she
was better after that and we were wondering what to do about it.
Who are those people,
those people that have been bothering.
This is the names you told me,
is it?
Yes,
they're called something like the brothers.
No,
you told me some names on the phone.
They are the same.
What some people are trying to do all this.
They seem to have attacked.
They're still there.
I think,
I think that
after we start burning the name and
you eating them every day,
their attack is more ferocious now so we're.
I saw that,
don't do it.
Yes
They,
they are all right.
They can fight it out.
They just do it.
No,
no.
Oh yeah.
Uh.
Really happy,
huh?
What about you having a baby sometime?
Not yet,
Mother,
but um,
I want to have one very soon.
Your house is not yet settled.
What happened to that house of yours?
The fellow was mad or what?
Oh,
I see.
So then what are you still in the same house?
Is it?
So Alan was thinking of uh.
arranging someplace,
Alan.
You were saying that there would be a
place together.
What about you people?
Who else?
Rosie and Rosie and me.
What happened?
We're looking for Rosie is looking for one in Bristol Bristol
on rent you would be,
it would be,
yes,
but um
landlords don't want
people who are having children and um
also there are a few of us who haven't got jobs and this doesn't help either.
How you can manage.
Uh,
why not give them also the same thing
which you are doing for Bristol,
uh,
for Brighton for Bristol,
the same thing,
just see this kind of a thing.
It's a very good thing if you can work at Chris Jessie,
have a look at it.
It's very interesting.
And
that is how we got,
I think.
So that you can use the Sergioga co op as a base.
hello hello
hello.
So your name is what?
Samuel Sam Samuel Mark.
So what should we call it?
OK.
OK,
what should we call it?
He's very strong,
mother.
Like Samsung,
Sam.
We have no Samsung.
First to call Simon a Samson,
many things I was,
but you should have another Indian name for him.
He was
honey.
Yeah
Oh
OK
OK.
Yes
Yeah.
So 11 month is the most powerful thing,
a month.
I uh.
Oh
So
movement.
I
The greatest in Bhakti is the highest.
Hanumanta is the highest in Bhakti.
No greaterhata is there than
Krishna has placed Ajuna.
Hanu Hanuman is the greatest because you see Ajuna is a human,
but Hanumanta is Bhati is so great that
he's a god.
Gods have their own powers,
despite that.
Devotion
is great,
isn't it?
The ones for gods to have this.
Human beings than that.
What
Who's speaking I'm on.
Angel and Jay's son.
Oh
Yeah
divorced the one who
who sustains his good name right.
Yeah
And you see,
I named him William and this also he is named as William.
Just look at that.
I think now everybody is going to call 1 million.
Yes
And now
You got me.
This is Marina.
Her name is Marina Marina.
No,
no,
no.
What happened?
What happened to you?
What
Yeah.
That's.
Why
Yeah.
Oh.
No
Yeah
Oh
Where is she?
None
Oh
Same thing is it.
Does she keep all right.
somebody else
OK
Why
Mm
Ah.
Why?
Why to cry.
In it or what?
You didn't go to any guru or anyone.
But I hope these horrible people are not working on him.
Yeah
Uh
To that
Did you take,
did you,
did you?
Meet them,
those people?
No,
you never took children there with them.
I think it was in Chile.
I've never been to Chile
they are back now here.
Not that they,
they operate on dead spirits and
they can
if they think of somebody in anywhere in the world they
they and this is what happened.
But they know about the child's birth and all.
They don't know nothing about Marin won't be able to know.
She's catching on the boy left,
left Rajasthan.
I don't know what.
She's part of.
been living with them.
Um,
a little girl and she's catching very bad sort of stuff.
Who,
who is she?
She's my brother's girlfriend's brother's girlfriend's daughter.
She has a very bad.
But what does she do?
This mother.
I think she's just a model,
and that's it.
Model that's fine.
You ask her to get out.
How is she in that house,
we had to move from our house,
so we had to move to.
Oh,
I see.
But now you're no more there.
feel like
Must be this modern business is dirty,
very bad.
It's very auspicious.
Hello,
hello,
Mara.
Why did you cry?
That may be the reason there's a lingering effect last time also I remember.
Oh.
One more
Let's see if she gets it.
Marina
That's it.
Thank God you're out of it now.
Horrible in
how they attack children.
This is very inauspicious to go for modelling and selling your body like that,
isn't it?
Models are nothing but just the very
poor type of women.
Why should you do it?
I just don't understand.
I'm sure she'll be all right now once you
get out of that place.
Oh.
Look at this one.
It's a tiger.
Oh.
Come,
come,
come.
Go.
Yeah.
No boy.
See the smile is very,
it's fallen off.
That's
Everything to be vibrated.
See that,
that's it,
that's it.
Now the movie that.
Remove the channel.
Remove everything that is,
uh,
at 3 3 ft level.
No.
you're gonna break.
Uh
Hoy,
he's
just finished some penicillin because he got
um croup,
croup it's it's heart.
It's breathing night,
but he's much better now.
He,
he had a bit of trouble breathing.
When I worried more he worried more,
so I stopped worrying.
You see,
if it is hot,
you should not suddenly expose children also as well.
I find that I don't know whether how hot he should be
and get overheated sometimes it's very difficult to know because in India,
but
40 days,
so they never allow them to want to see the sun that.
Hello,
Marina.
Are you all right now?
Are you better?
You had a bad liver,
I think
it also would penicillin worsen it?
How are you?
Is that my like.
You are yourself a liver being.
What else do you expect your child?
How is the speed?
Better now,
it rub it with some speed.
Oh my God,
he's not bad.
Oh.
Uh
I could be.
Junior varsity.
In
Watching the
You know that's your name.
Uh
Hello,
hello,
hello.
So full of life,
so full of life.
It's much better.
Hold on,
hold on,
hold on.
So
She's become very normal.
I think we'll have to get Susan also there.
Oh.
Yeah.
No,
I don't think so.
She's not,
not anymore.
He may not have brought up.
He may not have brought up all his wind.
I fed him not long ago.
Mm.
Hey.
Hey
I
It's slowly.
It's the.
You're rolling now.
He's going to put the right.
Hello
She gets normal.
I see they have everything
stupid like stupid person,
she cries now she's stupid.
What you need to cry for what
God has given you everything?
Did you cry,
you must thank God,
isn't it?
God has blessed you with everything.
Why should you,
uh,
we are happy.
Then be unhappy if you like it,
let us have it.
That's the main problem.
You never understand what God has you.
Mhm
Everyone unhappy,
right,
being unhappy you make everyone happy.
Hm.
I must tell you one news about the group.
This one Jew in Australia.
What's his name?
What did you say?
His name is Mr.
Finish that.
His name is also Rabbi.
He's a rabbi.
Do you have like that rabbi sketch?
The rabbi is the title,
isn't it?
means teacher actually.
It can't be the name.
No,
no,
that's the title,
but I don't know his actual name.
Uh,
I just thought maybe his name is.
Oh good.
Are you better now.
So
figure.
Yes,
so these new people have gone away,
have they?
Or they're going to come.
I think some of them are,
some of them are having lunch.
But it's gone.
Dumb he's not.
Hold on
You're going directly to Spain.
From London or are you going back to Cambridge?
Director.
Tomorrow,
tomorrow,
tomorrow.
Mhm
Tomorrow evening,
Uh,
Doctor Singh was telling me this that way,
but there's some writers were written.
That has
a
powerful electronics,
a powerful electronic
machine is there which makes everything indeed strong.
She said that some spiritual power is.
Which is where you can make
others spiritual or something.
I don't know what what he said.
That writer and another one who was saying
was
a
scientist
who has talked about.
TH Green,
you see,
he was telling me that TH Green,
uh,
is the person who has done.
Lot of research about you,
but and he speaks just like a surgeon.
Have you read PhD in any one of you?
So also ask him about this TH Green because
he did his uh
thesis on TH Green and uh no TH Green and uh Shankara.
I
So you might be able to get information about that.
That's one of the things you should let us know because
somebody's doing now a thesis,
is doing a thesis on yoga,
so we can bring in all these things.
Secondly,
what has happened about those ceramics I said from here?
What is it going?
They've got the permission.
They they've they've got to rented a shop in the best commercial district.
as well as the.
Well,
first of all,
they've got the letter from the agent so they can proceed with customs clearance.
They have not yet got customs clearance.
Secondly,
they've got
a property in the best business area of the city
for a small shop,
and thirdly they've got.
The
centre somewhere they wanted to have it for the opening ceremony they told me.
Well,
it looks as though they looks as though they.
See,
first they should do the opening ceremony
in the centre.
They wanted to invite people
from everywhere
and they were going to have an opening ceremony in that place.
Then they should go to this place,
to the shop.
First of all,
it is the start the centre they wanted to have some ceramics.
Isn't it?
That was the idea to start in the in the place we went to visit.
And then if they want they can start a shop,
but just now that is the best that you were going to.
The idea was that they would open that they would have an exhibition of the
ceramics you and they would invite all sorts of people
write to them this was the idea to invite
people for a new type of ceramics being created
and an exhibition of that.
And that they were saying we'll invite many people for that.
But I was thinking if Don could talk to Mr.
Singh and ask him who is the ambassador in Portugal,
I don't know who is he.
Indian ambassador,
if he would oblige them by opening the centre,
by opening the ceramics because it's Indian ceramics,
we should not call them Indian,
but Indians died ceramics,
that's it.
We're saying that we've got training from Indian
people or something like that,
not far from here.
All right,
so if just ask if somebody can inaugurate to see.
Because he has a very nice place for them,
then the whole thing will come up to a level.
I
What have they offered you as a job?
translate
I,
I'm filling in,
filling in for his translator while he's on holiday.
I think.
It's for 2.5 months.
To see for this later.
Uh,
what about Gerard?
What's the situation for him?
Did they say anything?
What's your wife's position?
Did you go and see her?
What did she say?
She's just waiting for the baby.
She hasn't said anything about science.
But now,
uh,
baby is expected when.
In October
Mountain
October.
So about 2 months more.
By that time,
uh.
You can find something for me?
Oh
So give him all the addresses,
everything,
and
all the people who are there.
You handle them carefully.
And I'm sure you can do very well.
How are your vibrations today?
How are you?
Oh
I leave all English complications
in England.
English complications.
This year
is.
Oh yeah
Hey
That are left now.
Are you feeling bad about it?
No,
you abundant.
You abandon to Roxanne.
All of you be abundant to her.
Put this 10.
And
You've got him.
The catches.
The Sudarshan who has come Sudarshan?
He's
he's come from Derbyshire I think.
Giren.
She's come here
from Oxford or from?
Is she here?
No,
she hasn't come,
but she's in Cambridge.
So Derek said she could help to show.
Hi,
it's all right,
she can go with you.
I,
she's all right.
Uh,
because after she's a grown-up woman,
what is there to be so frightened of anything?
After all,
Derek is going to be with her,
and she's,
she's a married woman with two children.
One daughter is in the matriculation class,
but she's also done a PhD in psychology,
you see,
just
PAD in psychology has to be frightened of everybody else.
Because they live in a pathological world,
they solve problems,
pathologies,
they treat people as if they're all sick,
you know.
Today,
Maureen was telling me she went and saw one book
that in a sense,
a myth.
Can you imagine?
For them,
in a sense,
the myth.
The other thing that is religion is an illusion of like opium.
What about psychology?
That is the God's gift.
According to them,
God is an illusion.
So how can it be God's gift?
This must be devil's gift.
Then
if God is an illusion,
psychology must be devil's gift the way they are destroying everyone.
They are destroying everyone.
Mother,
you do not know how they do it.
I'll explain to you.
Yeah.
He himself now he's convinced.
Now what I'm saying,
we'll have another book after your Jungian one about psychology.
You and Maureen put together,
bring them out in light.
See,
the first thing they do is they hit the liver,
you see.
First they let people have weak right sides anyhow.
They're all on the left,
then they hit the liver with that every psychological drug hits the liver.
Everyone immediately is put,
so then the liver goes and then there's no I mean it's all these tranquillizers,
these horrible and people have no chance.
If they still haven't recovered,
they shocked.
Yeah.
It.
No.
They.
Yeah
That.
I don't think.
Sorry.
See.
A decoguya
you know machinakotatikara.
Awn phoned me up twice.
How is she not very tired and she's got some information the rest and.
feeding the baby and she's a bit unhappy.
Oh,
she is,
she's she's still carrying out.
She'll be all right.
Loga baby.
Uh
I'm about to.
you
So,
so.
Huh
Give it to the mummy.
Good.
Uno.
What was theo ape Jesse the heart.
I.
William
William.
Well what bad is she,
Uncle.
Just
My bad,
bad.
Oh.
Oh,
Wow.
You
Yeah,
yeah,
OK.
It's beautiful,
isn't it?
I asked.
Er.
What's on his head,
oh.
S
Yeah
didn't give me any trouble to you.
Really nice.
He's very good all the time.
He's very sweet,
sweet.
Hello.
Hold the head,
I think.
He must be held.
Always put your hand under the head.
Yeah,
keep it.
Well Tina,
what Tina.
So should be the other food now
for lunch.
They've come back.
They ring a bell.
What about lunch.
I can have with you.
Yours is ready,
whenever you like.
Yours is ready whenever you'd like.
Mother said she'd have it with us.
How are you?
Are you better?
To Pamila.
Now you know why your
thing failed.
Mother,
I just wanted to say thank you for,
uh,
my,
my family.
I really
feel loved.
It's nice.
You're so much better.
You're going to come and see me,
right?
Yes.
How are you?
All right.
What about these two?
Have they come or gone?
Well,
they're here,
what are they?
I'm sorry.
You see why I asked you to go because yesterday I was very heavy,
and I couldn't raise the kundalini.
I just couldn't even
talk.
You see,
the weight was too heavy on me,
you see.
So that's why I said for Puja better not have you
because very intensive work it is,
you see,
and it cannot be managed.
But for her and we'll manage.
All right,
gradually you must cleanse yourself,
become lighter
and no use arguing.
Who was the girl arguing?
Where is she?
Yeah.
Somebody was arguing before the Puja.
Where is she?
Is that correct?
She must be having lunchchos.
I think she's from Bristol.
I think one from where I
think it was a lady from Bath.
She's not here today.
That's the best.
nicely.
How are you enjoying now?
Quite happy.
What about your house?
What they said they'd consider it.
You should find out something like uh veggies,
but it will be then you can be here.
Let's see.
What are they saying?
Well,
they're,
you know,
there's a lot of people more desperate than us
and to become homeless would be the only way
to get to homeless and then we have to go into bed
and breakfast to a bed and breakfast hotel so they can find
accommodation.
They don't consider them high on the priority list,
in other words.
That's why I try to go.
All right,
now I understand.
So
then I think you better do it in that case,
sir.
Oh
Oh you said you
That my head is not.
I have to have a big woman.
Hello by Matane.
Mata.
Oh,
thank you very much.
Is about.
But did you learn from I
I taught her how to make uh I know how to make her very simple.
You don't have to.
You saw that picture I'll show them.
It's very simple.
There's another
have to be done.
What
I