I bow to all the seekers of truth.
When we talk of truth we have to know that the truth is, was and will be.
We cannot organize it, we cannot change it and we cannot conceive it.
We have to understand it as it is.
But the truth that we know only through
our sensitive central nervous system,
like I see you all sitting here and also you can see Me
sitting here through you eyes is the truth.
Or the thing, you heard the music from your ears,
through your sense organs.
Whatever you have known through that, through your feeling is the truth.
It cannot be your imagination or your ideas which you have got in your
heads from your childhood or maybe that somebody has put it into them.
So we have to be honest in our seeking and whatever we have
found to be of no use or which is
not honest we have to give up.
Now whatever has been told to you about your chakras,
about your subtle being inside, all this is the knowledge of the roots.
We have through our science advance quite a lot.
We know lots of things that are existing but this is the knowledge of the roots.
Now as a scientist and as a scientific mind you should keep your
mind open to see whatever I am telling you is the truth or not.
So when we became human beings we developed
certain senses within ourselves in our evolution.
Like if you take a dog or a horse and ask them to go through a very dirty lane,
it will not feel hurt, it will just pass through.
But for a human being it is very difficult.
An animal does not understand anything that is beautiful.
Now we have achieved a lot as human beings but still
we have not achieved the absolute because there is so
much difference of opinion,
everybody thinks that he is correct and everything that we find is a chaos today.
So to achieve that absolute state something more
has to happen in our living evolutionary process.
What is that is already told to us in all our scriptures.
Christ has said that, “You are to be born again.” Now when He said that,
you cannot just take a certificate that I am
born again and go about saying, “I’m born again.” But when you are born again,
something has to happen within yourselves.
Today is your Independence Day and I congratulate you for getting your Independence.
But still we have to have our full freedom.
Because we succumb to temptations, succumb to falsehood,
we are tortured by people, oppressed by people, so many problems exist.
We have not been able to free ourselves of our problems
either physical or emotional or mental, even spiritual.
For this there is a very, very simple method of the last breakthrough.
For your evolution as human beings you did not pay anything,
you did not put any effort.
I have come here to give you the message that you don’t have to pay,
you don’t have to work hard, it is just there, you have just to have it.
You are all ready to get it, you are all ready to become that,
there is nothing to be done anymore.
Like one candle which is enlightened can enlighten another
light without any difficulty; in the same way it will work out.
By this you will become realized souls.
Like this instrument (the microphone) is prepared and unless and
until it is put to the main it does not work, it has no meaning.
So you are perfectly made for that,
only thing you have to be connected to the mains.
You will be amazed by this connection; so many things happen that
we can’t believe how we are so glorious and so beautifully made.
This is our own, our own property which is not known to us,
which you suddenly discover and you are amazed at yourself.
You get your real baptism and you find as cool
breeze of the Holy Ghost coming out of your fontanel
bone area which was a soft bone in your childhood
and the bone becomes also soft like a child’s bone.
Then you start feeling the cool breeze all around
yourself as very beautiful cool vibrations.
Such a person becomes extremely powerful, he becomes powerful with his compassion.
Wherever his attention goes he cures that
problem and such a person has a personality or a
temperament that when he is among the people who are disturbed and troubled,
their problems disappear.
The attention itself becomes collectively conscious,
means you can feel another person on your fingertips, the centers.
You can feel it within yourself, also what is wrong with you on your fingertips.
This is what has to happen to all of us when we become really peaceful
within and when we are peaceful, the peace spreads everywhere.
There are great organizations who talk of peace,
peace foundations, this peace and there is no peace within.
It is all artificial, men-made.
But when the human beings become peaceful within themselves,
there is no problem and they start enjoying each and everything of creation,
and the best thing, they enjoy are the human beings and one starts
understanding how beautiful God has created these human beings.
It is very surprising that so far I have not been able to come to such a beautiful
place for this work,
but I have been here before for some official work of my husband.
At that time,
I did feel the beauty of this place but there was not time to do this work.
I think this was the time I had to come and I am sorry for
being so late in my coming here; because once you become
that, you become the source of joy for yourself and for the
others and the Joy does not have duality like happiness and
unhappiness, it is an absolute thing;
you become the witness and start seeing the whole thing as big drama as if when you
are in water, you are afraid of getting drowned,
but once you came into the beat you can see all those waves with fun.
But when you are experts swimmers, you can save many who are getting drowned.
So this has been written long time back by William Blake,
that men of God that is the category
of people who are seekers,
will become so godly that they will start saving other people, So
though we find that in modern time there is so much of chaos,
so much of tensions, so much of
problems, there is one thing definite in this
special area only now people are seeking the truth.
I must have given many lectures on Sahaja Yoga and as you must have heard from
him that Sahaja means spontaneous and Yoga means the union with the Divine.
After the realization, you yourselves become the knowledge
but before that you better get your realization first.
Because say there are beautiful lights here and if you have to put them on,
I have to just say, that just press one button and all the
lights are coming; if I have to tell you about the history and all the
organization and everything of this electricity, it will be boring.
As a Mother, I would say, if I have done the cooking and if you are hungry,
you’ll just say, “all right, Mother,
now serve the food.” So there is no end to my talking about it,
it’s better we should have our Self realization.
May God bless you all!
I would of course like you to ask Me some questions for a short time,
and then the experience of Self-realization.
But please don't ask Me aggressive questions,
as I am not here in any way to take anything from you.
You cannot pay for your realization, you cannot pay for your curing,
and you cannot pay for anything that is good and is expressing within yourself.
Maybe it will work in most of you – I can see that – but maybe it may not;
it doesn't matter, it will work ultimately.
And we have here some very good people, Sahaja Yogis,
who can do marvels; they are very capable, very powerful people.
The change is within, not without; that is why,
though they look just like you, they are very powerful.
Let them ask some questions.
Do you have any questions?
Question (Q): Has sexual energy something to do with the Kundalini? Nothing.
It has nothing to do, is a wrong idea.
You see (on the Chakra chart) the red
chakra is the chakra for our excretion, for our sex energy.
The Kundalini stops at the gate of Christ, at the Agnya chakra because
if your eyes are very much wobbly then the Agnya chakra gets blocked.
But in Sahaja Yoga, we believe in beautiful marriages,
but not in funny type of perversions,
but we don’t have to tell you anything,
because you become your own guru, because Spirit is your master and
once you start seeing everything in the light, you yourself drop out.
For example, you are holding a snake in the darkness, you can’t see it and if
I say drop it, you will say, no I am holding a rope, why should I drop it.
But if there is light you will immediately drop it yourself.
So with realization you develop your divine
wisdom as well as your divine discretion.
Q: Are Sahaja Yoga and other types of yoga more or less the same?
You see every yoga that they talked of,
was established thousand of years back in India;
like you can say Hatha Yoga or Raja Yoga;
but the way these things are practiced today
are very unscientific,
because unless and until Kundalini starts rising you cannot say
where is the problem and if you do any exercise indiscriminately,
is going to harm you.
Q: Is the awakening of the Kundalini, that we shall get tonight,
something permanent, something that will occur just for a moment?
And what should we do to keep it?
Good question. It happens spontaneously and it just
works that moment but the Kundalini
is the one that emerges though your system, from your fontanel bone
area and She finds that there is a problem, say in you liver,
then She goes back there and starts working there on the liver to cleanse it.
So with the experience one start knowing how the Kundalini works on the various
centers then She starts establishing and is established in a permanent way.
As we can say when a seed is sprouting the little (premune?) sprouts and then you
have to look after the little tender plant for sometimes, then it becomes a tree.
Within one month time you become an expert and here you have a
center open every day where you will come to know everything.
Q: Kundalini is a force in itself, what is the way of increasing the power
of Kundalini and what
is the relationship
between Kundalini and the Spirit?
Spirit is the reflection of God Almighty and His Power is the Holy Ghost.
When He (the Spirit) and the Kundalini both of
them meet then it is like a little flame which
burns within our hearts as Spirit,
gets the force and the whole
thing becomes enlightened.
It is such as vast knowledge … once you have your realization,
it is better to understand these things in one light then to understand it
without lights: when we are in darkness, we cannot talk of the colors,
in the same way, let there be light, then we can understand it better.
Q: It’s quite a new knowledge; it is said it is dangerous to wake up
Kundalini when the chakras are not purified;
it is a fire that is burning.
What is your spiritual power that makes that the Kundalini
can come up and not damage us, and why is the time so short?
The first thing is absolutely wrong and false that the Kundalini gives you problems;
because people who do not know, who have no authority from
the Divine try to try some tricks on people; as a result of that the
deity of innocence gets angry and you get the result as heat in the body.
Now the Kundalini is the Primordial Mother,
your own individual Mother, your own Mother; when your mother gave your birth,
she took all the trouble upon herself and she did not give you any trouble, did she?
And She knows everything about you.
She knows your past, She knows all your weaknesses and She is so kind,
so gentle and She some way or another manages this second birth.
As far as Myself is concerned I don’t want to
say much about Myself because Christ was the Son of God,
He was the Path and He was the Gate and when He said that and people crucified Him.
That was the truth but people can’t bear the truth without realization.
I don’t want to get crucified because you know the time is so short.
Q: Is Sahaja Yoga the only way and what is the function of trantra yoga?
Tantra means the instrument,
actually in the pure sense of the word.
But those who called themselves tantrikas
are just the opposite of what is the tantra.
They know how to spoil your instrument, just to capture you,
it gives you the negative forces, just to take away your freedom.
They try to control your money, they try to control your family, this is not divine.
It’s black magic in a way, in a western language is black magic.
Q: Does the Word of the Holy Scriptures have something to do with the Kundalini?
Yes, yes and the description of the Kundalini,
of all this instrument is the Tree of Life …
Q: If the Kundalini has been, is and will be always in connection with the Spirit,
then why does the Spirit incarnate?
But the Spirit does not incarnate.
It’s quite a good question that we should have been born as realized soul,
what was the need to have the separation, is the correct question.
That’s what you mean?
The answer is very simple,
you know the story of Adam and Eve, everything was done so
well; if they had listened to God, we would not have gone through all the problem.
But they did not. They made a mistake;
this is the main original problem they created for us.
So we had to go through everything so called knowledge
which is not real knowledge and then come to this.
At human level you are given freedom.
But they never wanted to use the way God wanted them to use,
so they went in a roundabout way.
So God said alright, go ahead, find out for yourself and then He’ll
come and give at the last when you will be ready to receive the Truth.
And even now I am telling you can get it without any difficulty,
it’s your own right, you have it, it’s your own,
still people are finding it difficult in their freedom.
So that is human being you see.
He can’t accept anything.
They have to learn though making mistakes,
going into problems, then they learn it.
Sometimes they are too conditioned, sometimes they are too egoistical
and they cannot discriminate between the Truth and untruth.
Q: Right now Colombia is going through a very difficult period,
with a lot of violence.
Do you have any explanation of why this is happening here now,
and what is the method through which we can help it?
There are many things to be seen to that have created problems
of violence everywhere in the world – it is not only here.
But the problem comes from our wrong, man-made ideas.
For example, take democracy or communism – we have tried both.
In democracy, what we do is to allow an individual to have his own way:
let the individual grow, and we don't worry about the collectivity.
So the individual becomes important
and starts growing in a big way,
and he can become a madman who suppresses others, not caring about the collective.
And democracy is money-oriented: some make money and become greedy – money,
money, money, like mad – so you become rich, but you also become wilder.
In the communist ideology they worry about the collectivity
and not about the individual, so the individual
becomes absolutely weak and helpless;
and what is the use of doing things collectively with weak people?
So both ways have failed.
A very powerful politician from London came
and told Me that she is fed up with the left
and the right and wants to be in the centre,
so she is starting a party in the centre.
I said, what is the use?
If you are in the centre, you will have no movement.
These are all man-made ideologies.
If you are in the centre, you should be ascent-oriented;
then you become a very different personality.
I would say: supposing I have all the powers, I am a capitalist – but I am
also a communist, because I cannot enjoy it by Myself, I must share it.
So all these man-made theories get integrated in Sahaja Yoga,
and you start really enjoying the truth after Sahaja Yoga.
In Sahaja Yoga the individual is nourished, is balanced and enjoys his joy,
and the whole collectivity is within him – he can feel the whole collective.
And we do not live with theories, but with the truth.
You can feel the truth: supposing you want to know, is there God?
Just put out your hands and ask the question,
and you start getting the tremendous, nice vibrations, filled with joy.
Now, let Me ask the majority – what does the majority want,
realization or questions? [The audience asks for realization.]
So, better have your realization.
You can write down your questions and I will try to answer them; it is not endless.
Again I give you the message: if the food is ready, it is better to eat it.
I wish all of you could sit down, because you don't have to see anything anymore.
And those who do not want to have their realization should go,
because it will disturb
others; if you have no desire for it,
it is better that you leave the hall, without any anger.
I was very happy to learn that in this country Mother Earth is highly respected.
The chakra which controls the innocence – and also the abode
of the Kundalini – is made of
the element of Mother Earth.
Now I would request you all to take off your shoes and put your feet
on Mother Earth, if possible, so that she takes away your problems.
Those who are sitting on the ground need not,
but take off the shoes; it also increases the attention.
Everybody can sit down – there is nothing to be seen – you can sit in the passage,
it is all right.
I did not expect so many people to come.
Now I have to tell you that in our procedure we put the left hand towards Me,
very comfortably,
like this.
The left hand is the power of your desire, symbolic of your desire to achieve
your realization; keep it comfortable,
with the fingers pointing towards Me.
The right hand is used for the power of action, to release your chakras,
and it will also teach you how
to raise your own Kundalini.
The first and foremost thing is that we have to enter into the Kingdom of God,
and you are at the epitome of your evolution now.
That is why you should not feel guilty at all; you should be happy.
After all, human beings can only make mistakes – we are not God.
So forget the past, just forget the past, and be here in the present.
Do not count your mistakes,
do not count your miseries – just be happy with yourself and have love for yourself.
This is the basic condition: only happy people can enter the Kingdom of God.
So forgive yourself, forgive yourself.
Now please close your eyes; you can take off your spectacles,
because you don't have to see anything.
Put your left hand towards Me and your right hand on your heart,
and close your eyes.
Here you have to ask Me a question – “Mother,
am I the Spirit?” – ask it three times; it is a very fundamental question.
Watch yourself, not others;
this is the only time you have to see yourself, so keep your eyes shut.
This question means that if you are the Spirit,
you become your own master, your own guru.
Now put your right hand on the upper part of your abdomen,
on the left-hand side, and ask Me another question three
times: “Mother, am I my own master?” Now take your right hand
to the lower part of your abdomen, on the left-hand side.
Here I cannot take away your freedom; in your freedom you have to say six times,
“Mother, please give me the pure knowledge,” because this centre has six petals.
As you ask, the Kundalini starts moving upward; make way for the Kundalini.
Now take your hand to the upper part of your abdomen,
on the left-hand side, and say with full confidence ten times,
“Mother, I am my own master.” Now raise your hand to your
heart and say with full confidence twelve times, “Mother, I am
the Spirit.” We have to know that the Divine is the ocean of love,
grace and bliss, but above all it is the ocean of
forgiveness – so we have to forgive ourselves;
for what mistake can we commit that this ocean of love cannot forgive?
Now raise your right hand to the corner of your neck and shoulder,
turning your head to the right, and say with full confidence sixteen
times, “Mother, I am not guilty at all”; and if you still feel guilty,
say it a hundred and eight times, because you are not guilty.
Now put your hand across your forehead and press it on both sides;
this is the centre of forgiveness.
Say, “Mother, I forgive everyone.” You may say it is difficult,
but it is a myth – whether you
forgive or not; and if you do not forgive,
you play into wrong hands, so it is better to forgive.
Say it from your heart.
Now take your hand to the back of your head and rest your head on it;
for your own satisfaction,
without feeling guilty and without counting your mistakes,
say, “O God, please forgive me for
whatever I have done wrong.” Now stretch your hand on top of your head,
over the fontanel bone area
– this is very important – stretch your fingers,
press it down, and move your scalp seven times.
As I cannot force you, ask Me in your own freedom: “Mother,
please give me my Realization.” Move your scalp seven times and ask seven times.
Now please take down your hands and slowly open your eyes.
Watch Me without thinking.
Stretch your right hand towards Me and put your left hand on top of your head,
bend your head, and see
for yourself whether there is a cool breeze coming out of your head;
some people get it close, some far.
Now change hands and feel with the right hand.
Push back your head and ask three times: “Mother,
is this the cool breeze of the Holy Ghost?
Is this the Chaitanya?
Is this the all-pervading power of God's love?” – ask any one of these, three times.
Now put down your hands and feel the breeze.
Those who have felt it, on the fontanel bone area and on their hands,
please raise both hands.
I bow to all of you – you are divine people.
Now you have got it; so beautiful it is.
I don't know how I will leave Bogota tomorrow, leaving you all here.